Register of the Jaquelin H. Hume papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jaquelin H. Hume papers,
1964-1991
98068
Hume, Jaquelin H.
37 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 framed photograph (15.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, lists, and financial records, relating to Republican Party fundraising activities, especially in California, election campaigns of Ronald Reagan, especially his presidential campaign in 1976, and the gubernatorial and presidential administrations of Ronald Reagan.
Administrative Information
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Jaquelin H. Hume was born in Harbor Point, Michigan, on July 17, 1905. He received his bachelor's degree from Princeton University in 1928 and his M.B.A. degree from Harvard University in 1930.
During Ronald Reagan's first term as governor of California, he was appointed chief of protocol for Northern California. He was also heavily involved in the Republican Party's fundraising activities, especially in California, and in various political campaigns, both at the state and the national levels, especially in the presidential campaign of Ronald Reagan in 1976. That same year he served as co-chairman of the Northern California Finance Committee of Citizens for Reagan.
In addition to his public activities, Jaquelin Hume was an active businessman: he was president and director of Basic Vegetable Products, and chairman and director of American Potato Company, both in San Francisco. He also served on the board of directors of Leslie Salt Company in San Francisco, and of Trader Vic's and Trader Vic's Restaurants, Inc.
He died in San Francisco, California, on October 1, 1991.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Jaquelin H. Hume papers were donated to the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998 by his son George H. Hume. They relate mainly to the election campaigns of Ronald Reagan for governor and for president, and to Jaquelin Hume's involvement in those and other campaigns of Republican candidates, both at the state and at the national level. The collection bears testimony to Hume's important role in the Republican Party and to his outstanding organizational and fundraising abilities.
Indeed, the fundraising activities file is the most extensive series in the collection, and covers a period of over 20 years. Of particular interest therein is the large amount of correspondence, the profiles of candidates for whom he raised money, and the records of contributions of various committees and organizations to the campaigns of Ronald Reagan and other Republican candidates. Citizens for Reagan is especially represented here, as Hume was co-chairman of its Northern California Finance Committee.
The Government service series relates to Hume's tenure as chief of protocol for Northern California during Ronald Reagan's first term as governor of California, from 1967 to 1970, and consists mainly of correspondence with various officials in the Reagan administration. Please note that some of this correspondence is addressed to Hume as president of Basic Vegetable Products, Inc. (A speech he gave to the employees of that company in 1965 can be found in the biographical file.)
Other political correspondence can be found in the main correspondence series, with interesting letters to and from Ronald Reagan, Howard Baker, Michael Deaver, Edwin Meese III, and Lyn Nofziger, among others.
Finally, the subject file contains important material on Ronald Reagan's presidential campaign of 1976, and on Jaquelin Hume's involvement with the effort to lower taxes in California.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Elections--California.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Citizens for Reagan.; Reagan, Ronald.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; California--Politics and government--1951-
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1965-1976 (Folder 1)
  Certificate of selection as a delegate, speech, and miscellany relating to the personal activities and accomplishments of Jaquelin Hume, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Certificate of selection as a delegate to represent the state of California at the Republican Party's national convention, 1976 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Speech given to employees of his company, Basic Vegetable Products, Inc., at Vacaville, California, on the occasion of the presentation of award pins to employees who served in the company for 10-30 years, 1965 December 15 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1977-1990 (Folder 1)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Baker, Howard H., Jr., 1987 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Baldridge, Malcolm, 1985 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Caldwell, Alan, 1988 (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes a letter to Edwin Meese from the Pacific Legal Foundation
  - Clark, William P., 1985 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Cranston, Alan, 1988 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Deaver, Michael K., 1985 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Deukmejian, George, 1977 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Du Bain, Myron, 1988 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Feulner, Edwin J., Jr., Heritage Foundation, 1989-1990 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Hallett, Carol, 1989 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Johnson, Ross, 1988 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Milbank, Jeremiah, 1981 (Folder 1: 15)
    Includes a letter and a memorandum to Holmes Tuttle
  - Nofziger, Lyn, 1981-1988. Includes a proposal for educational reform from the Sequoia Institute (Folder 1: 16)
  - Nolan, Pat, 1987-1988 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1985-1990. (Folder 1: 18)
    Includes correspondence with James S. Rosebush and Robert H. Tuttle
  - Regan, Donald T., 1985 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Ronald Reagan Presidential Foundation, 1988 (Folder 1: 20)
    Includes an invitation to participate in the groundbreaking ceremonies for the Ronald Reagan Presidential Library and Center for Public Affairs, 1988 November 21
  - Smith, Jean (Mrs. William French Smith), 1990 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Tuttle, Holmes, 1977 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Vuksich, Dorothy (Mrs. Raymond Vuksich), 1990 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Miscellany, 1981-1990 (Folder 1: 24)
- Government service file, 1967-1970 (Folder 1)
  Correspondence, invitations, letter of appointment, lists, memoranda, messages, notes, organizational chart, reports, clippings and other printed matter relating to the activities of the office of the governor in general and of Jaquelin Hume as chief of protocol for Northern California in particular, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence with various members of the governor's office, including Ronald Reagan. Includes correspondence addressed to Jaquelin Hume as president of Basic Vegetable Products, Inc. (Folder 1)
    - 1967-1968. Includes some 1966 correspondence (Folder 1: 25)
    - 1969. Includes some 1970 correspondence (Folder 1: 26)
  - Invitations, 1969 (Folder 1: 27)
    Includes some letters of Ronald Reagan stating that Jaquelin Hume will represent him at various government functions
  - Letter of appointment, Chief of Protocol, Northern California, 1967 January 16 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Lists of the Deputy Chiefs of Protocol, Northern California (Folder 1: 29)
  - Organizational chart of the governor's office (Folder 1: 30)
  - Public relations appointee file, 1968 (Folder 1: 31)
- Fundraising Activities file, 1965-1989 (Folder 2-17)
  Agenda, correspondence, profiles of candidates, and records of contributions relating to the campaigns of Ronald Reagan and other Republican candidates, both at the state and at the national level, and to efforts by Jaquelin Hume and others to raise funds for those races, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes materials relating to activities of Citizens for Reagan
  - General (Folder 2: 1)
  - Agenda (Folder 2: 2)
  - Correspondence. Includes related materials (Folder 2)
    - General (Folder 2)
      - 1965-1968 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1968 (Folder 2: 4)
      - 1968 July - 1969 December (Folder 2: 5)
      - 1969 December - 1970 December (Folder 2: 6-7)
      - 1970 June-October. Includes correspondence relating to Jaquelin Hume's financial contribution to Vanderbilt University for their television news project (Folder 3: 1)
      - 1971 March-November. Includes Jaquelin Hume's comments re U.S.-Japanese relations (Folder 3: 2)
      - 1973 (Folder 3: 3)
      - 1973-1974 (Folder 3: 4)
      - 1974 (Folder 3: 5)
      - 1974 March - 1975 January. (Folder 3: 6-7)
        Includes letters by Glenn Campbell, then director of the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace
      - 1974 April (Folder 3: 8)
      - 1974 November - 1975 June (Folder 4: 1)
      - 1975 July - 1976 February (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1975 December - 1976 February (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1976 January-July (Folder 4: 4)
      - 1976 February-December (Folder 4: 5)
      - 1976 March-December. (Folder 5: 1)
        Includes records relating to the candidacy of John A. Sutro
      - 1976 May (Folder 5: 2)
      - Foster, Charles A., Jr. (Folder 5: 3-5)
      - Lee, Ivy, Jr. (Folder 6: 1-2)
      - Princeton University. (Folder 6: 3)
        Includes record of Jaquelin Hume's personal contribution to Princeton University
      - RR 100 Club (Folder 6: 4)
  - Financial records (Folder 6: 5-10)
  - Profiles of candidates. (Folder 6)
    Includes other materials as noted
    - Barbagelata, John (Folder 6: 11)
    - Brian, Earl. See also John L. Harmer (Folder 6: 12)
    - Curtis, Carl and H. L. Richardson (Folder 6: 13)
    - Flournoy, Houston I. (Folder 6)
      - General (Folder 6: 14)
      - General (Folder 7: 1-2)
      - Financial records (Folder 7: 3)
      - Memoranda (Folder 8: 1)
      - Proposal (Folder 8: 2)
    - Ford, Gerald R. (Folder 8)
      See also Citizens for Reagan. Northern California Finance Committee
      - General (Folder 8: 3-5)
      - Lists (Folder 8: 6)
    - Hallet, Douglas L. (Folder 8: 7)
    - Harmer, John L. (Folder 8: 8-9)
    - Livermore, Putnam (Folder 8: 10)
    - Reagan, Ronald (Folder 8)
      - General (Folder 8)
        - 1973 (Folder 8: 11)
        - 1974-1975 (Folder 8: 12)
        - 1976 (Folder 8: 13)
          See also Records of contributions
      - Delegates file (Folder 8: 14)
      - News releases (Folder 9: 1)
    - Reagan, Ronald - George Bush (Folder 9: 2)
    - Reagan, Ronald - Gerald Ford (Folder 9: 3)
    - Ueberroth, Peter (Folder 9: 4)
    - Van Camp, Brian (Folder 9: 5)
    - Weinberger, Caspar (Folder 9: 6)
    - Younger, Evelle J. (Folder 9: 7)
  - Records of contributions. (Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence and other related materials
    - General (Folder 9)
      - General (Folder 9)
        - General (Folder 9: 7-9)
        - General (Folder 10: 1-2)
        - Documents to justify the legality of the funds (Folder 10: 3)
        - Lists (Folder 10)
          - General (Folder 10)
            - Lists of names (Folder 10: 4-10)
            - Lists of names by county (Folder 11: 1)
          - Reagan lists (Folder 11: 2)
          - Miscellaneous political lists (Folder 11: 3)
        - Rules re contributions (Folder 11: 4-5)
        - Telegrams (Folder 11: 6)
      - California (Folder 11: 6-8)
      - North and South Dakota (Folder 12: 1)
      - Ohio (Folder 12: 2)
      - Pennsylvania (Folder 12: 3)
      - Wisconsin (Folder 12: 4)
    - California Committee to Elect a Republican Legislature (Folder 12: 5)
    - Citizens for Reagan. Executive Steering Committee (Folder 12: 6)
    - Citizens for Reagan. Northern California Finance Committee (Folder 12)
      - General (Folder 12: 7-11)
      - Correspondence (Folder 13: 1-2)
      - Minutes (Folder 13: 3)
      - Miscellany (Folder 13: 4)
    - Committees formed to support Ronald Reagan's candidacy for governor and president. (Folder 13)
      - General (Folder 13)
        - 1969-1970 (Folder 13: 5)
        - 1969 December - 1970 March (Folder 13: 6-7)
        - 1969 December - 1971 March (Folder 14: 1-2)
        - 1970. Includes some 1969 correspondence (Folder 14: 3-5)
        - 1970 January-December (Folder 14: 6-7)
        - 1970 January-December (Folder 15: 1-2)
        - 1970 February-November (Folder 15: 3)
        - 1970 March - 1971 January (Folder 15: 4)
        - 1970 April-July (Folder 16: 1)
        - 1975 November - 1976 June (Folder 16: 2)
      - Membership records (Folder 16: 3)
      - Memoranda re corporate contributions (Folder 16: 4)
    - Nixon-Agnew Finance Committee (Folder 16: 5)
    - Republican Congressional Boosters Club (Folder 16: 6-7)
    - Republican National Finance Committee (Folder 16: 8-9)
    - Republican Party (Calif.) (Folder 16: 10)
    - Republican Party (Calif.) (Folder 17: 1)
    - Republican Party (Calif.). State Central Committee (Folder 17: 2-3)
    - Republican Party (United States) (Folder 17: 4-5)
    - United San Francisco Republican Finance Committee (Folder 17: 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 17: 7)
- Subject file, 1966-1990. (Folder 17-20)
  Includes correspondence, flyers, memoranda, newsletters, reports, speech, statistical information, telegrams, clippings and other printed matter relating to various individuals, organizations, and political issues, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - American Enterprise Institute (Folder 17: 8)
  - California (Folder 17: 9-12)
  - Citizens for America. Typescript notes for a phone conversation between Jaquelin Hume and Ronald Reagan (Folder 17: 13)
  - Crane, Phil (Folder 17: 14)
  - Economic assistance (Folder 17: 15)
  - Flat-rate income tax - United States., Includes writings of Robert E. Hall and Alvin Rabushka, Fellows at the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace (Folder 17: 16)
  - Flat-rate income tax - United States (Folder 18: 1)
  - Goldwater for President Finance Committee (Folder 18: 2)
  - Meese, Edwin III, 1987-1990. (Folder 18: 3)
    Includes copy of his article, "What Lesson From the 1980s?"
  - Nelder, Al (Folder 18: 4)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1969 (Folder 18: 5)
  - The Political Lineup (Folder 18: 6)
  - Public schools - United States. Speech by David T. Kearns (Folder 18: 7)
  - Reagan, Nancy (Folder 18: 8)
  - Reagan, Ronald. See also Fundraising Activities file (Folder 18)
    - Governorship, 1966-1974 (Folder 18)
      - General (Folder 18)
        - List of state officials appointed by the governor (Folder 18: 9)
        - Printed matter (Folder 18: 10)
        - Program for revenue control and tax reduction submmitted to the California legislature by Ronald Reagan, 1973 March 12 (Folder 18: 11)
      - Environmental protection - California (Folder 18: 12)
    - Presidential candidacy, 1975-1976 (Folder 18)
      - Briefings file (Folder 18: 13)
      - Clippings (Folder 18: 14)
      - Record of trips. Includes related correspondence, memorandum, and schedule (Folder 19: 1)
      - Presidency - Inauguration, 1980 (Folder 19: 2-4)
      - Miscellany (Folder 19: 6)
  - Republican National Convention. List of delegates (Folder 19: 7)
  - San Francisco (Calif.). Port Transfer Committee. Includes materials relating to Jaquelin Hume's participation in the Port Transfer Committee established by Joseph L. Alioto, Mayor of San Francisco, to negotiate the transfer of the port from the jurisdiction of the state to that of the city, 1968 (Folder 19: 8-9)
    Includes correspondence with Joseph Alioto 20.
  - Taxation - California. (Folder 19: 1-4)
    Includes materials relating to Californians for Lower Taxes, creation of a tax lobby and Jaquelin Hume's personal contribution to the creation of a tax lobby, and Proposition 1
- Photographs, 1980 (Folder 21)
  1 print of an unidentified individual, n.d.; 1 print, one copy and one negative of a group of unidentified individuals, n.d.; and one postcard of president Ronald Reagan issued by the United States Capitol Historical Society, 1980
- Oversize file, n.d. (Folder 22)
  Map of the United States indicating the number of delegates by states
- The remainder of the collection is undescribed. (Folder 23-38)